What comes to your mind when you hear
the term bread first search? If you're
thinking about a graph, that might be
the reason you find some problems tricky
to solve. What I want to show you is
that if you think about a Q, that can
make your life a little easier. Hello
friends, welcome back to my channel.
To get a better understanding on the
bread first search coding pattern, you
must first lay down the foundation on
which a bread first search actually
works. So let us go back to the basics a
little bit and try to understand what is
actually happening. For example, when
you see bread first search, you can
apply it at a lot of different places.
The first example that you can think of
is a binary tree. So what happens when
you do a breadth first search in a
binary tree? The idea of a breadth first
search is actually very very simple.
What you need to do is you need to start
somewhere. Let us say this is the node
that I'm starting with and then you try
to find out all of the connected
components of the first node that you
started with. I have identified two
connected components. What is the next
step? you iterate over each of the
connected components and then find out
okay what other nodes are connected. So
this time I'm going to find out more
nodes. Once you are done with these also
now is the time for these new nodes and
once again you will try to find out the
connected components.
So this is actually bread first search
and I want you to remember it in this
particular way and you're shortly going
to see how this will simplify
everything. What happens if you have an
ner tree that means a child could have n
number of branches. How do you apply
bread for search over there? If your
fundamental concepts are clear it
shouldn't be a problem for you. So over
here I start off with my first node.
Okay. And now find out all of the
connected components directly to the
first node. You identified these. Now is
the time that you iterate over each of
these nodes. And once you do that, which
nodes will you look? These are all the
four nodes that you will look upon. Do
you still have nodes remaining? You will
iterate over each of these nodes and try
to find out the connected components.
And then you found out okay these are my
connected nodes. And this is the way you
conducted bread's first search at each
of the levels even in your nertory. Now
comes the interesting part. What happens
in the case of a graph? And does this
logic to do a breadth for search also
apply over here? The interesting part
and the fun part is yes. How do you
approach it? Start anywhere that you
want to. Let us say I'm starting off
from my first node over here and I have
to do a breakfast search. What concept
did we follow? You need to look at all
of the connected components. So this
node is connected and this node is
connected. For the next iteration, what
do you do? Look at each of these nodes
and find out all of the connected
components. So this is connected. Then
this node is also connected to this
node. This node is also connected to
this node. And that is it. This
particular node isn't connected
anywhere. So that is where you stop. But
you still have more nodes to visit. So
this time you are going to look at
another nodes. This particular node is
connected to this node and this last
node is connected to this node over
here. And now you have covered every
node in your graph. And you were able to
do a breadth first search once again. So
your idea still remained the same. You
started off at a particular node, look
at the connected components and then you
go from over there. That is the idea and
that is the pattern you have to follow
to solve a lot of different questions.
If you remember I told you in the
beginning you need to think about a
bread first search in form of a Q data
structure. How? Let us say I have this
graph in front of me. How can you
implement a bread for search first using
a Q? Take up this Q data structure and
let us say I'm starting off with a
particular node. What you do is you put
this node in your queue and now you want
to iterate over this entire cube until
it is completely empty. And what do you
do at every iteration? You pop out an
element. I will pop out this element. It
means I need to look at this particular
element and find out all of the
connected components. How many nodes do
I have connected to one? I have two
connected. I have three connected. I
have seven connected and I have six
connected. So if I will be doing a bread
for search, I have two 7 3 and then a
six. The algorithm says that whatever
node you popped out, get all of its
connected neighbors and put them in your
queue. So what will happen over here? I
will get four nodes added in my queue.
You are now done with node number one.
So you can safely remove it. Remember
how long do you have to run until your
queue is completely empty. So now what
you can do? Remove node number two over
here. And what do you see? You want to
see all of its connected components. You
have already visited node one. You have
node five. This is the next level. So
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
take this node and I'm going to add it
in my que. What is happening over here?
This Q is ensuring that I will iterate
all of these elements in the order that
I appeared. So this particular node
appeared first. Then I had all of these
nodes. So my cube will process all of
these nodes. Then the next level. These
are all of the nodes I am going to cover
next. So just watch what happens. I am
now done with node two. So what I can do
is I can safely remove it. Time to pop
out another node. I popped out three. So
I look over here. I have already visited
one. But I still need to visit four. And
I will add it in my queue. I'm done with
node three now. And this is how you are
going to continue. The next note I have
is six. How many neighbors does six
have? Six has one as a neighbor, but you
have already visited. Then you have
eight as a neighbor. This eight also
gets added to the queue. You are now
done with node six. So remove it. And
now you pop out node 7. So seven has one
neighbor, but you have already visited
it. It doesn't have any more neighbors.
So you can remove it. Now pop out five.
Five doesn't have any neighbors.
Similarly, you will pop out four and
eight. They don't have any neighbors.
Your queue will be finally completely
empty. And that is how you know you have
traversed your entire graph. You did a
breadth of search. And you can see that
this concept will apply to any tree, any
ner tree or even any graph. And that is
the idea we will be using. Even if you
think about a grid, this is a very good
indication that this will involve a
bread for search. Why? Because a grid is
nothing but a graph. You can think about
all of these cells just as different
nodes and all these nodes are connected.
So when you would do a breads for
search, just remember your basics again.
Let us say I'm starting with this
particular cell. What do you do? put
this cell in a que and look at all of
the adjacent neighbors. These are all of
the neighbors which get added to the
que. Now what will you do? You will pop
out each neighbor one at a time and look
at all of its neighbors. So what will
happen? Now you are going to cover all
of these elements. Once you're done with
this level, now you will cover the next
level. You can see that how you are
going to expand your entire search space
and eventually you will be navigating
your entire matrix. It just might be
possible that you will have separate
conditions. That means you could only
have once available in this matrix and
you can only go over there. You could
only go horizontally and vertically. You
cannot go diagonally. These are all the
constraints which you will find in
different set of problems and we are
certainly going to see all of that. But
what I want you to focus right now is
the idea we are choosing. How we are
thinking about a bread for search. How a
Q data structure will actually help to
implement all of this. Let us now
quickly start taking at a list of
problems that you can easily solve with
a bread for search algorithm. You might
have already guessed the first problem
that is doing a level order traversal in
a binary tree. I don't know why it is
written as a different problem. You all
know about an inorder traversal and post
order traversal and a pre-order
traversal. How is a level order
traversal different? Well, the idea is
you are not following any tree property.
What you're doing is you are going level
by level. And if you think about it, it
is just a breath for search. So what I'm
doing, I start off with the first node
and this gets added to my que. This is
your beginning point. And for every
question that involves BFS, this will be
your starting point. Just take up a
value and put up in your queue. And now
you want to run a while loop until this
Q is completely empty. And what do you
do in your loop? You pop out an element
and then look at all of the neighbors of
this particular element. Whatever
neighbors do you get? Just take those
neighbors and add it in your que. Once
you're done traversing all of the
neighbors, just remove the element that
you popped out. Now remember, you are
running a while loop until your que is
completely empty. So pop out a new
element. So you want to look at its
neighbors also. So these elements will
also get added to the que. This element
is now gone. This time you're going to
pop out six. Six has the neighbor seven.
So seven also gets added to the cube.
you will continue on this way and
eventually you will traverse all of the
nodes in a certain order. So what did
you do? You determined a level order
traversal of your binary tree. All you
need to make sure is that you insert the
left element first and then the right
element. You insert the left element
first and then the right element. This
way you are ensuring that you are going
in a left to right direction. If you
don't look at this ordering, it might be
possible that you enter one in your
queue, then six might get added and then
two. So this doesn't become a level
order traversal. You might get another
question. Okay, how many levels do I
have in the tree? As soon as you have
found out all of the neighbors, just
insert some kind of a marker in your
view or a dummy value. As soon as you
get this dummy value, it means a level
has been completed. Once you encounter
these two values, again, insert a dummy
value. Once you encounter these three
again insert a dummy value. This way you
are finding the number of levels in a
binary tree. What about a zigzag
traversal? It means you are traversing
like this then like this then like this
and then like this. So what do you do?
For the first level insert the right and
the left. For the next level insert a
left and then the right. And then for
subsequent levels you just keep on
alternating the order. That is the idea.
But the basic concept of maintaining a
cube and popping out elements will
remain the same. Another problem that
you might have seen is minimum depth of
a binary tree. How do you measure the
depth? So a tree can have several
branches. But what is the terminating
node? Any node which doesn't have any
more children that is a terminating node
and that is telling you a particular
depth. So this node is at a different
depth. This node is at a different depth
and this node is at a different depth.
You have to tell me the minimum depth
and you can see that this is the minimum
depth. So how can you approach this? Can
you apply the level order traversal
here? Yes. Because if I start to
traverse my tree like this, I get the
first level and every node has children.
Then I look at the second level. Every
node has children. I look at the third
level. Node three has children. Node 5
does not have any children and that is
where I immediately stop. I don't even
need to traverse the rest of the tree
because I found a node that doesn't have
any children. I want to look at the
minimum depth. It means this is the
first node that I want to return. This
is giving me the answer. So you can
immediately say whatever level this
particular node is on and this will be
your answer. This is the minimum depth
of this binary tree. Pretty simple,
right? And if you're getting the drift,
there is one more problem that becomes
really easy to solve. The left view of a
binary tree. Over here you are given
this binary tree and you have to do a
different kind of traversal. Instead of
a pre-order level order in order, what
you're doing is you are looking at this
tree from the left side. So you have to
tell me what nodes are visible. So you
can see that node one will be visible,
two is visible, three then four and then
a nine. If you apply any traversal
techniques, it may become so hard to
even think about it. Where do you even
begin? How do you determine if is this
the leftmost node? But a breadth search
or a level order traversal comes to your
rescue. What do you need to do over
here? Iterate level by level. you are
doing a breath of search and for every
level capture the first element that
you're getting.
These are all the elements that you will
encounter when you are doing a left view
of the binary tree. A breadth for search
makes things super simple. Similarly,
you could have another problem where you
want to do the right view of the binary
tree. It is literally the same problem.
When you're iterating over every level,
just keep a track of the last element
that you're seeing and voila, you found
the answer. This is how things can
become super simple. For example, you
have another problem average of levels
in a binary tree. Do you really think it
is a different problem to solve? All we
are doing is we are doing a breadth for
search or a level order traversal to
iterate over each of these levels and
you just find out the average of every
level. This keeps things super simple.
You are only doing a single iteration
and you don't even have recursion. You
know the time complexity it is going to
be order of n because you are iterating
all of the nodes only once and that is a
good time complexity to have and these
are just some of the ways how you can
apply a bread first search to tree type
of problems. However, the application of
BFS isn't limited. If you remember we
talked about graphs also. So how do you
apply the bread first search when it
comes to problems on graphs. Let us
start off with a basic but important
problem to get you warmed up to the idea
of using Q's bread for search using
graphs. Over here I have this problem
number of provinces and then I am given
a matrix. This matrix is defining if a
cell or a node is connected to one
another. For example, when I check node
one, it is connected to node 6 and it is
connected to node 9. So one is connected
to six and one is connected to 9. And
similarly, you will find that node 6 is
connected to one and node 9 is also
connected to one. If you want to find
the information about any node, for
example, node number four, you can look
up in this matrix. So node four is
connected to node two and node 4 is also
connected to node 7. So node 4 is
connected to two and seven. This is how
this matrix is defining all of my
connected components. The problem
statement says that if you are given
this matrix and all of these cities, you
have to tell me how many provinces are
there. Basically, if you find clusters
like these, then these all are
provinces. So for this particular
problem, three should be your answer
because check this out. Nodes five and
eight aren't connected to any other
components. All of these nodes are
connected to each other in some way or
the other. So how do you apply BSS over
here? Or how do you apply the Q data
structure? What ideas come to your mind?
For example, as soon as you see a graph,
try to think about a breadth for search.
What happens if you apply the breadth
for search? Let us say I'm starting off
with any node. I started off in node
one. And if I try to apply a breath for
search, what will happen? I will
navigate at node 9 and I will navigate
at node 6. Can I go any further? No. And
what did I do? I covered all of the
nodes that were reachable from node one.
Right? So that's it. I can stop over
here. I can make my province count plus
one. I know that I have at least one
province. Correct? How do you proceed
further? What you can do is you can look
for node number two. And where do I have
node number two? I have it over here.
Now again start to apply the bread for
search. I start from this particular
node. Now look at all of the connected
components. Two is connected to node 3.
Two is connected to node 7 and two is
connected to node 4. Once again I cannot
go any further. All of these nodes are
done. So my breadth for search stopped.
So what can I say? I may have discovered
one more province. So I can say that
okay I am going to set the number of
provinces to two. What next? How do you
proceed? Look at node three. Do you want
to apply bread for search on this? No.
Why? Because you have already visited
it. So what you can do is you can also
maintain another array that is storing
each of the nodes that you have visited.
So what were you doing while applying
the bread for search? You started from
node one. Mark this as visited. You
reach node 9 and six. Mark these as
visited too. This is because when you
will encounter them later, you know that
you don't have to solve for them. When
you started off in node two, you marked
this as visited, then three as visited,
seven as visited, and four as visited.
All of these nodes are marked visited.
That is why when you started off with
three, you know that you don't have to
solve for it. Do you have to solve for
four? No. Because you have visited it.
Do you have to solve for five? Yes,
because this node is still not visited.
So apply the breakfast for search. You
start off with this and then you find
one connected component. You mark both
of these nodes as visited and you cannot
perform BFS further. Maybe you found
another province. So what you will do?
You will set your number of provinces to
three. Now keep going ahead. Check out
node six. This is already visited. Check
out node 7 already visited. Node 8
already visited. Node 9 already visited.
Now you have covered all of your cities.
You have exhausted your entire list and
what do you have? You have determined
the total number of provinces that you
had. So a BFS is actually helping you.
You were just using the Q data
structure. You applied a certain logic
to solve this entire problem. And this
is the coding pattern that I'm talking
about. This was however one of the
problems where you could immediately
construct the graph and you could also
immediately apply the BFS algorithm.
Sometimes it may not be evident. For
example, there is a problem available
called course schedule. In this problem,
you are given a list of all of the
courses and courses have prerequisites.
For example, take a look at this
particular schedule. What you are
basically given is you are given arrays
like this 1, 4. So 1A 4 is telling me
that you need to take course 1 before
taking course 4. Then you are also given
9A 4. That means you also need to take
course 9 before taking course 4. This is
how all these different arrays are
given. This particular test case is
viable because you can see that you will
be able to ultimately take all of the
courses. There is no cyclic dependency.
A invalid test case will look something
like this. For example, it is saying to
take course one, I have a prerequisite
of course 4. To do course 4, I need to
do course two. Up till here, everything
is fine. But check out this dependency
also. To do course two, I need to do
course one. So this is kind of a
deadlock. It can never happen. Right? So
this particular test case is not valid.
So given these two test cases in this
problem you have to tell me whether a
course schedule is even possible or not.
For this you will return true as your
answer and for this you will return
false as your answer.
How do you solve this problem or rather
how do you apply the breadth for search
in this particular problem? Let us take
up a valid scenario and one thought
might be immediately clear in your mind.
I have to use the Q data structure and I
have to start somewhere. What can be a
good starting point? Check out all of
these courses. What is special about
them? These courses do not have any
prerequisites. You can start all of
these courses immediately or you don't
have to wait for anyone. So what are
they? These are good candidates to be
your starting points in a breast search.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to
mark all of these courses as my starting
positions. And what do I do? I mark all
of these courses in my queue as well.
What did you just get? You now have a
starting point. And how can you proceed?
You need to run a while loop until this
que is completely empty. And how do you
proceed? You take out the first course.
What can you do after completing this
course? After completing this course,
you can do course number four, right?
But do you want to put this course in
your queue yet? No. Because you have one
more dependency on your course. So what
we're going to do over here is for each
of the courses you are going to maintain
a map that is telling you that what is
the end degree of a particular course.
So what I will have over here is some
kind of a table that is storing the in
degree of each of these nodes. The in
degree means how many dependent courses
do I have. And you can easily construct
this from your input array. So course 4
has two in degree, course 3 has two,
course 5 has one, and course 8 has two.
So I'm going to write down all of this
in my map. And when you're popping
elements, you popped out one. So check
out its neighbors. its neighbor is four.
What does it mean? It means you can
reduce the end degree of this particular
node by one. So what will happen? This
two gets reduced to one because you have
completed this course and one doesn't
have any other neighbors. So I'm done
with it. What do you do now? You pop out
the next element. The next element is
nine. What courses can you complete with
it? Check its neighbors. You see course
four again. So what will you do? try to
reduce its end in degree because you
have completed it. So this gets reduced
and this now changes to zero. As soon as
the end degree changes to zero, it means
you have completed all of its
prerequisites. So what can you do? You
can basically take up this node and add
it in your queue over here. It means
that I have completed this course and I
am ready to process it in my queue. I
may need it later to determine if I have
completed all of my courses or not. So
what will happen next? You will
encounter two. Then you will encounter
seven. Both these courses will get
completed and they will reduce the
degree of three to zero. So three will
also get added to your queue. Over here
you know what is going to happen next.
You are going to pop out four and then
you will look at its neighbors. You will
see five. Five has it in degree of one.
This gets reduced to zero and then node
five will go in your queue for
processing. This way you keep on
proceeding until your Q is completely
empty. If your Q becomes empty at
certain point, it means that you will be
able to complete this course schedule
and you can return a true as your
answer. Try to think what will happen in
a case when this scenario is not even
possible. For this particular test case,
where can you start? Okay, you will
start off from a node which has a end
degree of zero which doesn't have any
dependencies. You add this to your que
and now what happens? Five has a end
degree of two. So this gets reduced to
one. Correct. But do you have any other
node to work with? No. Because no other
node has a end degree of zero. So what
happens in my map? I will have some
elements that still have some kind of an
end degree. It means I cannot even reach
that course. I am unable to complete all
of the prerequisites. In that case, you
return false as your answer. This
example was really great because you
have to try and figure out okay what
will be my starting point. You were
already seeing that this problem has
nodes and it has connected components.
But sometimes you might have a problem
where the nodes are also not even
visible to you. For example, take up
this problem, minimum genetic mutation.
The idea over here is that you are given
a certain gene structure and then you
have to determine can you transform it
to this particular structure and the
condition is that all of these values
can be just set of four characters
either A, C, G or T and they can be in
any order. You are also given a
condition that whenever you change any
character, let us say I change this
particular character to G. Then this is
your current string. You are given a
certain dictionary if this is even valid
or not. You have to tell me after how
many mutations what is the minimum
number of mutations required so you can
reach this particular mutation. This
problem feels very complex when you
think about it. It may feel that oh my
god I need to have so many permutations.
How do I validate it? How do I check it
in my string? Where do I go? But BFS is
your helper over here. How? If you think
about it, this particular node, this
itself is the starting node. And what
about your child nodes? How do you get
them? If you convert each of these
characters and mutate it into a
different character, you will get your
new nodes. For example, if I change this
A to a C, what do I get? I get this
particular string and this is a new
node. What if I change this? Then I get
this particular string. This is my new
node. I can change this C to a G and
then I get this. I can change this C to
a G and then I get this. So what I'm
getting? I got an initial tree or a
starting point and then this tree it has
four children. What is happening? It is
becoming an ner tree. Actually, it will
have more combinations possible and each
of these nodes they will have
permutations of its own. The idea of a
breakfast search will still remain the
same. You are going to take this entire
string and pop it in your cube. Pop out
a single element, get all of its
different permutations.
Then pop out another element and get all
of its different permutations. the extra
dictionary that you have to determine if
a mutation is even valid or not that
will help you to eliminate your entire
subree. For example, this is a mutation
but the problem may say that this is not
valid. So you will remove this entire
subree. It just reduces your search
space but the entire concept will still
remain the same. I particularly don't
like these kind of problems. But if you
ever encounter these, BFS is again your
friend over here. I really think now
you're understanding where can we apply
the breadth for search and how do you go
about it. Once you have determined the
starting point, the idea becomes
relatively easy. So there are certain
cues which can help you determine if a
breath for search can be actually
helpful for you. For example, first of
all, there should be a finite state
space. There should be a finite number
of elements you have to look from. From
all these examples that we saw, there
are only certain possible conditions and
then you are searching amongst them.
Breth for search is just a technique by
which you iterate over all of them
efficiently. What are we doing? We are
going level by level to cover the entire
search space. And when you're doing it,
it is not necessary that you have to
start from one root node. You can start
parallelly also. You can start from
nodes that are independent. For example,
look at the course schedule problem. You
can start from any course that doesn't
have a dependency and then you can work
from your way over there. So these are
some of the cues that can help you
identify that a breath first search
might be applicable to this problem. Up
till now we have covered three type of
problems where you can apply the breath
first search. We have covered some
graphs. The remaining portion is
problems that involve a grid or a
matrix. And if you remember I told you a
grid is nothing but a graph that is
connected or disconnected in a certain
way. You might have seen problem like
this. Maximum area of an island. You are
given a water body where all the
elements if are zero they are water and
if they are one they are a land
structure. You have to tell me which
island has the largest area. Where do
you even begin? Once again BFS is your
friend. What you can do is start
iterating over your matrix. As soon as
you see any element as one start
applying BSS. So I cover this add this
to your que and look at its neighbors.
You added these to your neighbors and
they get to the queue. Now pop them out
and look at its neighbors. You covered
all of these elements. You marked all of
these nodes as visited and you are done.
You found the area that this is four. So
possibly four is my maximum area. You
left it over here. Right? Now iterate
ahead. Once again you found an element.
Start your DSS. You start from here and
then you cover all of these nodes. You
are done. But the area is still four. So
you don't do anything. You move ahead,
you see one more one, but this note is
visited. So you're going to skip it. You
move ahead, no other one. Then in the
next row, you find another one. Apply
your BFS. You start here. Then you find
the next level. And then you find the
third level. And then finally the last.
So you found another greater area. And
this area is eight. So you update your
area. you are done. If you start to
iterate any one that you encounter now,
they all have been visited. So you're
not applying DFS again and again. At the
very end, you will find one more one. So
you try to traverse it, but that's it.
You found your maximum area that is
eight. And that is your answer. What
were we doing? We just applied the BFS
technique as soon as we got a starting
point. Also notice we just traverse
every element only once because if we
encounter it again a visited array helps
us to know if we need to perform BFS
again on it or not. On a similar idea
there is one more problem available
rotting oranges. Once again you're given
a grid and this grid has some oranges.
What happens is that for each of these
orange groups you are given a orange
that is rotten. So let us say I'm
starting off with a rotten orange. You
have to tell me in how many days will
all of the oranges get rotten. And the
idea is that in the next day all the
neighboring oranges will get rotten. So
technically what is this telling you? It
is giving you the starting points of
your BFS. You start from over here and
then you apply BFS one time. So this
happens and for the third group it is
completely rotten. What next? On the
third day this group is completely
rotten and then on the third day you
still have some oranges remaining. What
happens on the fourth day? This last
orange also gets rotten. So how many
days did you take? You took a total of 4
days. What were we doing? We were
applying a bread for search. We just
started from the rotting orange in the
first place and then kept on expanding
until we are able to cover all of the
finite search space that we have. That
is why I told you if you get the
fundamental correct all of these
problems become very very easy to solve.
Let us quickly look at one more problem.
Shortest path in a binary matrix. You
are given a matrix like this. You have
ones and zeros and you have to determine
the shortest path from this top left to
bottom right. The idea over here is that
the path has to consist of only once.
You can see that there are multiple
paths possible. You can traverse like
this. You can traverse like this. You
can traverse like this. There are
multiple ways possible. But what is the
shortest path? What do you do? You apply
the bread first search. You start from
over here. In the next iteration, where
can you go? You can either go here or
here. You took two steps. In the next
iteration, you can go here or you can go
here or you can go here. So you are done
with three steps. In the next iteration,
you can go here or you can go here or
here or here. Because I'm assuming that
you can go in all the eight directions
from a point. The problem can trick you
that okay, you can only go vertically or
horizontally, not diagonally. then you
might need to tweak on how you are
completing your search space. Up till
now we have covered four steps. What
about the fifth step? Now you know that
this is not going to lead you anywhere.
For the fifth step, you can reach here,
here or here. For the sixth step, you
can reach here, here, here or here. So
what did we do? In just six steps, we
can reach the final destination. If you
want to actually get the path, then you
might have to implement some additional
logic to find out this path that you
covered. But you know that a bread first
search is your friend and this is how
you can explore your complete search
space. I think now you are getting a
good hold of how you can apply the bread
first search in a lot of different
coding patterns. To master this
technique, first of all, you determine
the starting point. This is the place
where you start exploring. What do you
do next? You start to explore outwards.
It depends upon the problem that you are
given. Can you go in all the eight
directions? Can you go only left and
right? Can you go only bottom and right?
Just make sure what you have because
that is how you're exploring a left tree
or a right tree. You have a ner tree.
How are you exploring that? In the next
part, you have to manage your que. How
are you popping elements? when are you
adding them back? For example, in course
schedule, you want to add an element
back to your queue only if the in degree
is zero. These are some things to watch
out for. Once you have done all of this,
you are now determining a path. You want
to keep on iterating until your Q is
completely empty. And then once your Q
is completely empty, you have ultimately
found out the solution. You just need to
validate it and you need to determine if
this is the required output or not. So
what did we learn from all of this? Just
a simple BFS technique can solve a lot
of different problems if applied in the
correct way. That is why I was
emphasizing you need to understand BFS
from the point of view of a Q because a
Q is helping you process all of these
elements in a first in first out order.
And that is the USP of a bread first
search. That is the underlying idea how
a bread first search actually works. So
if you found any problems while going
throughout this entire video, do let me
know or tell me what other problems that
you have found that follow the same
pattern. It will become a really good
collection and it is going to help
anyone who is watching the video in the
future. As a reminder, if you found this
video helpful, please do consider
subscribing to my channel and share this
video with your friends. This really
keeps me motivated and I can make more
such videos. Also, a huge shout out to
all of the members who support my
channel. you guys really keeping going
and as a member you do get private reply
to your comments and early access to new
videos as well. Also, you can now
schedule one to one sessions with me and
we can discuss about almost anything.
Stay tuned for my upcoming video. Until
then, see youa.